When I'm in first grade
等我上了一年級
I hope I can make 100 friends
希望能交到100個朋友…
She's from our school.
她是我們學校的學生吧？
This is Itan Private High School.
這裡是私立伊旦高中
A well-known prep school.
是縣內知名的明星學校
I've always been average,
沒想到至今這麼平凡的我
but I got into this school.
也能進這所學校
I can't get ahead of myself.
但我不能太貪心
For now, my goal is
總之現在的目標
to read the room and not make waves in high school!
是要對周遭的人察言觀色 過一個平靜無波的高中生活！
That's all I need.
這樣就行了
That's all I want!
這樣是最好的！
Tadano is a coward.
只野同學是個膽小鬼
One thing I know,
我知道
is reading the room and not standing out
看周遭氣氛行事，低調生活
is the way to happiness.
那才是通往幸福的捷徑
It's not like I stood out in junior high.
並非是因為國中時 為了表現個性而吃到苦頭
It's not like I made a fool of myself. Not at all!
不是因為這個原因！絕對不是！
Um… greetings are important.
打招呼是很重要的
Our shoe lockers are close, so we're in the same class.
妳也使用這裡的鞋櫃 表示我們是同班對吧？
Good mor…
早…
ning…
安
Wow! So beautiful! Praise prep school! Long live prep school!
天啊，超級大美女！ 不愧是明星學校！明星學校萬歲！
Uh.
喔
CREAK… SNAP!
（僵硬轉頭）
Huh?
什麼？
Huuuuh?
什麼啦？
Yikes! Is something wrong?
怎麼了？我做錯了什麼嗎？
Have I done something wrong?
我是做了什麼不該做的事嗎？
TAP TAP TAP TAP TAP
（快步前進）
What was that just now?
剛剛那是怎麼回事？
"Komi"?
“古見”同學？
What was up with her?
那個人到底是怎麼了？
At any rate,
不過話說回來
she sure was pretty.
-早安！ -她是個美女
Hey, same class!
我們同班呢！
Yay!
太好了！
An ordinary guy like me won't ever be involved with her.
不過我這種凡人 應該不會再跟她有什麼交集
My life here will be…
我的高中生活
peacefu… oh.
要過得平穩
She was seated next to him.
她就坐在隔壁座位
Huh?
什麼？
Whoa. So beautiful!
天啊，好美啊！
She smells nice.
她好香喔
Komi.
古見同學
Although it's the first day of school,
看來她第一天上學
she is already the most admired girl here.
就已經建立了校花的地位
I mean…
這個嘛…
I'm happy to be seated beside the prettiest girl in school.
能坐在校園第一美女的旁邊是很開心
But somehow…
但總覺得…
I feel like there's a target on me.
我感受到了一股殺氣
If he were gone, that would be my seat.
只要那小子消失 就能輪到我坐在她隔壁了
Tadano…
只野
Tadano's high school life
只野同學的高中生活
was full of rough waves from the start.
從一開始就掀起了波瀾
KOMI
（古見同學）
Introduce yourself.
自我介紹吧
I'm Agari!
我叫上理！
N-Nice to m-m-meet…
還請大家多多關照！
Agari, take it easy!
上理同學太緊張了啦
Oh good! A friendly class.
太好了，我們班上的人好友善！
Next!
下一位
Um.
呃
Huh?
什麼？
Uh.
喔
TAP TAP TAP TAP
（快步前進）
CLASS ROSTER
（班級日誌）
WOW!
哇！
Huh?
什麼？
Next.
下一位
Here.
是！
I'm Hitohito Tadano.
我叫只野仁人
Let's have a great year.
這一年還請大家多多關照
My specialty is reading the room.
我的專長就是會察言觀色
Just kidding.
開玩笑的啦
-Tsk. -Huh?
-呿 -唉
-He's not reading it. -Next.
-根本不會察言觀色嘛 -下一位
Tadano realized that his high school life
只野同學很快就瞭解
was over before it began.
他的高中生活已經完了
KOMI
（古見同學）
Listen.
聽好了
Write this down if you tend to forget what to bring.
如果怕忘記明天要帶什麼就快寫下來
First, gym clothes.
首先是體育服
Make sure you write your name on them.
號碼布要寫上名字並貼好
On your gym shoes too, before you forget.
要在體育館穿的鞋子 也趁現在把名字寫上
Everything she does looks beautiful…
她無論做什麼，都美得像一幅畫
Huh?
什麼？
You dropped your eraser.
妳的橡皮擦掉了
COMPASS
（圓規）
What's his deal?
這個人是怎樣啊？
I'd better hand it over quick or I'm dead!
我得快交給她，不然會沒命！
BBBRRRZZZZZZZ
（顫抖）
Huh?!
什麼？
Tadano pretended he didn't see.
只野同學決定假裝沒看到
KOMI CAN'T…
（古見同學…）
Bow!
敬禮！
Next class is in the gym.
下一節課在體育館
My name is Hitohito Tadano.
我的名字叫只野仁人
I started high school today.
今天起我就是高中生了
My goal is to not make waves.
我上了高中之後的目標是 度過平靜無波的高中生活
KOMI!
（古見同學）
A perfect goal for an average guy like--
對於各方面都平凡無奇的我而言 這是個恰如其分的目標…
Oof!
啊！
Hey Komi, want to eat lunch together?
古見同學，要不要一起吃午餐？
Komi!
古見同學！
Or so I thought.
-本該如此 -交換聯絡方式吧！
I love you!
我喜歡妳！
Why can't I…
我為什麼會…
Someone's talking?
有人在說話？
Why can't I talk in front of people anymore?
變得沒辦法在人前說話？
Was I asleep?
奇怪，我睡著了嗎？
-Meow. -Oh no!
-喵 -糟了！
Next is gym!
下一節課要去體育館！
Ah!
啊！
Um.
不是的
Uh,
那個…
I didn't hear anything.
我什麼都沒聽到
Hang on!
等等！
Dang it!
完了！
She said "Meow."
她說了“喵”
And I said "I didn't hear anything." So I totally did.
被我這個同班同學聽到 我卻硬要說沒聽到
This could linger in her memory forever…
這種心理創傷 可能會永遠留在她的記憶中
I've got to fix it! Fix it now!
圓場！總之我得打圓場才行！
Uh.
啊
Komi, I'm not sure, but…
古見同學，妳該不會是…
Are you not good at talking to people?
不擅長跟人交談？
What am I saying?
我在說什麼啊？
No way that's possible! She's the most popular girl in school!
那怎麼可能，她可是校花耶！
Rude. That was so rude of me.
-沒有啦，我的意思是… -失禮，我真是太失禮了！
Uh.
那個…
Ah!
什麼？
Um.
呃
TREMBLE
（顫抖）
Komi? Komi!
古見同學？古見同學！
You really are bad at speaking.
原來妳真的不擅長跟人交談
Well done.
你竟然察覺到了
TADANO LEVEL UP! COMPREHENSION +3 EXP
（只野同學升級！理解力加3！）
What were you trying to say just now?
妳剛才想說什麼？
TREMBLE
（顫抖）
Oh. This won't work.
還是不行
Is there some way we could communicate?
我得找個辦法和她交談
Oh!
對了！
What if you write on the board? We can talk by writing.
或許可以寫在黑板上 用筆談的方式溝通？
Oh!
喔！
WRITING ON THE BLACKBOARD
（正在黑板上寫字）
HOW DID YOU KNOW THAT I'M NOT GOOD AT TALKING TO PEOPLE?
（你為什麼會知道 我不擅長跟人交談？）
I just kind of guessed by your reactions.
我是從妳至今的反應猜到的
Hasn't anyone noticed before?
話說回來，以前都沒有人發現嗎？
NO.
（是啊）
Oh, wow.
啊，這樣啊
I've already run out of things to say!
這麼快就無話題可說了！
Next is gym class, right?
對了，下一節是在體育館上課對吧？
I'll go on ahead.
我先過去囉
HE FLEES!
（只野同學逃跑！）
This is so awkward.
這氣氛我受不了！
Ah! Huh?
啊！
WAIT.
（等等）
W-Wa-Wai…
等等…
But he can't escape!
可是他逃不掉
I guess she has something to say?
她是有什麼話想說嗎？
I COULDN'T EAT MY LUNCH.
（我以前都沒辦法吃便當）
Oh, are you hungry?
妳肚子餓了嗎？
Ah!
啊！
I REALLY DO WANT TO SPEAK.
（其實我很想和人交談）
MY FACE FREEZES AROUND PEOPLE.
（我在別人面前會很緊張 表情就會僵硬）
I GUESS I'M SCARED, BUT I WANT TO SPEAK.
（雖然非常害怕 其實我很想和人交談）
Oh…
原來如此
BUT WHEN I APPROACH PEOPLE, THEY GET NERVOUS.
（可是每次我一靠近 對方就會緊張，甚至昏倒）
SOME FAINT OR EVEN COWER IN DIRT.
（還曾經有人對我下跪）
I THINK THEY HATE ME.
（大家應該很討厭我吧）
-NO, I KNOW THEY HATE ME. -There's been a huge misunderstanding.
-（不，我知道大家一定很討厭我） -這個誤會可大了
WHEN I WAS IN JUNIOR HIGH,
（國中的時候）
IT WAS SO HARD, ESPECIALLY DURING LUNCH.
（午餐時間我總是很難受）
I HATED EATING ALONE.
（一個人吃飯很痛苦）
EVERYONE WOULD CHAT AND EAT.
（看著大家都是邊聊天邊吃飯）
I WAS SO LONELY.
（我很難受）
I TRIED TO TALK EVERY DAY FOR THREE YEARS.
（在那三年裡 我每天都試著跟大家交談）
BUT MY VOICE WOULDN'T COME OUT.
（但我卻發不出聲音）
NO MATTER HOW HARD I TRIED.
（無論我怎麼嘗試都沒辦法）
I COULDN'T TALK TO ANYONE.
（就是沒辦法向別人搭話）
WHAT SHOULD I DO?
（我該怎麼辦？）
HOW CAN I TALK? WHAT SHOULD I DO AFTER THAT?
（我該怎麼搭話？ 開口交談後又該怎麼辦？）
WHAT IF THEY REJECT ME? WHAT SHOULD I SAY NEXT?
（如果遭到拒絕怎麼辦？ 接下來我該說什麼？）
WHAT IF THEY SAY I'M BORING?
（要是別人嫌我說話無趣怎麼辦？）
IF I CAN'T SMILE RIGHT, THEN WHAT?
（如果我沒辦法面帶笑容怎麼辦？）
WHAT SHOULD I DO?
（怎麼辦？）
I WANTED TO ASK YOU TO EAT LUNCH WITH ME.
（我好想問別人要不要一起吃飯）
She went through so much, just trying to say one thing.
只是要說出那一句話 對她來說竟然是這麼困難的事
Komi isn't hard to talk to, nor hard to approach.
看來古見同學並非高不可攀 也不是難以接近的人
You can use this.
這個拿去用吧
She's just…
這個人…
a regular gir--
只是個平凡的女孩
-I JUST HAVE HICCUPS. -Huh?
-（我只是在打嗝） -什麼？
Did your hiccups stop?
打嗝已經止住了嗎？
YES, THANKS.
（真不好意思）
No problem.
沒關係
I CAN'T EVEN SAY GOOD MORNING.
（我甚至沒辦法跟人打招呼）
EVERYONE ELSE CAN DO IT. BUT I CAN'T.
（別人都做得到，就只有我不行）
FUN THINGS. HAPPY THINGS.
（高興的事、開心的事）
TALKING ABOUT MISTAKES. STUDYING. LAST NIGHT'S TV SHOW.
（失敗的經驗、課業學習 昨天看的電視節目）
I CAN'T EVEN TALK ABOUT THE WEATHER.
（就連聊今天的天氣 我都沒辦法做到）
I'M SORRY.
（對不起）
-I'M SORRY I BOTHERED YOU, TADANO. -Tadano!
-（我給只野同學添麻煩了） -她寫了“只野同學”！
I DON'T KNOW HOW TO MAKE IT UP TO YOU.
（我不知道該怎麼補償你）
Huh? Were you bothering me?
妳有做什麼虧欠我的事嗎？
ANYWAY.
（總而言之）
She dropped it.
被直接跳過了
I THOUGHT I SHOULD APOLOGIZE.
（我覺得必須向你道歉）
I'M SORRY.
（對不起）
I'M SORRY I WROTE SO MUCH.
（抱歉寫了這麼多廢話）
GO AHEAD AND FORGET WHAT YOU SAW HERE TODAY.
（你可以把今天在這裡 看到的一切都忘掉沒關係）
GOODBYE.
（再見）
ISN'T THE WEATHER NICE TODAY?
（今天天氣真好，真是太好了）
YES.
（是啊）
TRY WRITING MORE.
（試著多說一句）
THE CHERRY BLOSSOMS WERE PRETTY.
（櫻花很漂亮）
IT'S OKAY. RELAX.
（沒事的）
SHOOTING STAR
（流星）
WHAT'S YOUR DREAM, KOMI?
（古見同學的夢想是什麼？）
I WANT TO MAKE 100 FRIENDS.
（交100個朋友）
PLEASE DON'T LAUGH.
（請不要笑）
I'LL BE YOUR FIRST FRIEND, AND I'LL HELP YOU FIND THE OTHER 99.
（那我就當妳的第1個朋友 我會幫助妳結交其他99個朋友）
JOLT
（僵住）
BLUSH
（臉紅）
ERASE ERASE
（擦掉）
THANK YOU SO MUCH.
（那就拜託你了）
HUH?
（什麼？）
DASH
（奔跑）
Hey, Komi!
啊，古見同學！
POP!
（臉紅）
This is how my abnormal high school life began.
於是我那不平凡的 高中生活就此揭開了序幕
My goal?
目標是…
To help Komi, someone who isn't good at talking to people…
幫助不擅長跟人交談的古見同學…
Oh.
啊
"Someone who isn't good at talking to people" is so long.
“不擅長跟人交談”聽起來不順口
Not good with people…
“社交”
Difficulty communicating…
“不擅長交流”
Communicate…
“交流”…
Oh!
對了！
My goal.
目標是…
To help Komi who can't communicate make 99 friends!
幫助有交流障礙症的 古見同學交到99個朋友
When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所謂的“交流障礙症” 是指不擅長和人交流的一種症狀
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有這種症狀的人
Bear in mind, they only struggle to form connections.
不過需要注意的是 這些人只是不擅長社交
It doesn't mean that they don't want to.
但並不表示他們不想和別人有往來
Good morning.
早安
One thing I know,
我知道
is that Komi is beautiful.
古見同學長得很美
Of all the people I've seen, she's definitely the prettiest.
在我所見過的人當中 她絕對是排名第一的大美女
Her skin is pure white.
肌膚白皙
Her eyes are big and almond-shaped.
有一雙大大的鳳眼
Her hair is smooth.
秀髮光滑柔順
She smells good.
而且還香香的
It's like she gleams.
總之就是很耀眼
Komi!
古見同學！
I mean…
沒事
Good morning, Komi.
早安，古見同學
G-Good…
早…
TREMBLE
（顫抖）
Um.
我想想…
We've got to start with some vocal exercises.
對了，首先應該練習一下發聲
Try saying, "Let's be friends."
那麼請說說看這一句 “請跟我做朋友”
If you can say that, you'll have 100 friends in no time.
只要會說這句話 妳一定馬上就能交到100個朋友
PETRIFIED KOMI
（古見同學石化了）
Komi?
古見同學？
One thing I know,
-我知道… -古見同學？
is that Komi can't communicate well.
古見同學她有交流障礙症
Not only that.
我還知道
She really wants to talk to people.
她是多麼渴望和別人交談
I know that too.
我深知這一點
And that Komi…
我和這樣的古見同學…
Okay, one more time.
那再來一次
…is my friend.
成為了朋友
But Tadano has missed something.
不過只野同學他還沒發現
Their school, Itan Private High School.
他們所就讀的私立伊旦高中
Though it's a famous prep school, entrance is based on interviews alone.
雖然是縣內數一數二的明星學校 是否能入學只靠面試決定
To pass, students must be unique.
該校的入學合格基準是個性
Yes, it's full of…
沒錯，這就是一所…
freaks,
奇人
weirdos,
怪人
loners,
邊緣人
miscreants,
異端者
and eccentrics.
一堆個性獨特的人聚集的學校
Tadano hasn't yet realized
只野同學他還沒發現
how difficult it's going to be…
古見同學要在這所學校交到朋友…
for Komi to make friends at this school.
是多麼困難的一件事
Oh!
喔！
BONUS SCENE
（片尾彩蛋）
"She was very beautiful."
“她非常美麗
"Her milk-like skin glowed in the room light
如牛奶般的肌膚 在屋內燈光的輝映下
with a reddish tinge."
泛著淺淺一層紅暈
"Her long, delicate arms and legs didn't seem to be from a life in poverty."
她的手腳纖細，看她嬌弱的模樣 應該不是出身自窮人家
"Shortly after the old woman left the room,
老婆婆走出房間，不久後
the girl spoke with a slight accent."
少女用帶點口音的腔調說道”
Alright, now continue.
好，接著換人唸
Komi.
古見
Whoa.
天啊！
Yes! You're so right!
嗯，是啊！
What's the point of reading aloud? There is none!
讓學生朗讀課本 其實一點意義都沒有！
Alright, everyone read silently!
好，大家默默讀課本就好！
KOMI WAS JUST TOO SHY TO SPEAK.
（只是緊張得發不出聲音）
Action!
開拍！
-Hey Komi! -Your notebook!
-古見同學，筆記本拿反了！ -古見同學！
-Yeah! -Good!
-對！ -這樣就對了！
THE END
（結束）
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻譯：馬慈光